斯坦福大学
> Stanford University.
欢迎来到CS193P课程 2013-14秋季第18讲
> Okay. Well, welcome to lecture number 18 of CS193P, fall 2013/14.
在我讲今天要讲的内容之前
Before I talk about what I'm going to talk about today,
首先谈谈后面有些什么
let's talk a little bit about what's coming
因为我们这学期已经接近尾声了
up because we're right at the end of the quarter here.
周三的下一讲
So on Wednesday -- next lecture --
将是备选期末陈述日
we are going to have this alternate final presentation day.
你们有些人已经说了要进行陈述
And a few of you have already said that you wanted to do that.
如果你想在周三进行陈述
And really, the only thing you need to do to sign up to do that if you want to use
而不是在常规的期末陈述时间
this Wednesday as opposed to the following Thursday normal final presentation
来进行陈述
time to do your presentation,
你只需要在明天中午12点前提交Keynote幻灯片
is to submit the Keynote slides, okay, by tomorrow at noon.
这很重要
That's very important.
如果明天中午12点我们没看到你的幻灯片
If I don't see your slides by tomorrow at noon,
那么你就不能在周三进行陈述
then you're basically not going to be presenting on Wednesday.
那你就只能在周四进行陈述了
And then you'll be forced to present next Thursday.
关于Keynote幻灯片我只想说一点
So the only thing I'll say about your Keynote slides,
记得做成宽屏格式 1280乘以720
make sure that they're widescreen format, okay, 1280 by 720.
如果你是用PPT或别的什么来做幻灯片
If you are submitting PowerPoint or something else, you know,
提交后就得看运气了 因为我会将其转为Keynote
you're taking your chances because I'm going to convert them to Keynote.
如果字体这些转换正确 那你运气就蛮好
So if they have fonts and stuff, convert them -- you're in good shape; if not, you know,
否则 你的幻灯片可能会看起来很糟糕
you're slides might look a little wonky.
你们只需要正常提交
You just submit them normally, right?
只需要按照常规课堂提交脚本来
Just do the normal class submit script.
作为期末项目提交
You submit it as your final project.
当然 你还可以重新提交 直到截止时间
And of course, you can submit again, all the way up until the deadline.
周三在学生进行完期末陈述后…
And the other thing we're going to do on Wednesday after we have a few people, you know,
顺便说下 我建议大家都来
do their final presentations -- which by the way, I, you know,
并为这些人担当听众
really encourage all of you to come and be an audience
这样你们就能够听到别人的期末陈述是怎么做的
for those people just because you'll get to see some final
这对你有额外的好处
presentations; you'll get a little bit of bonus.
我会简单讲到期末陈述
I'll talk a little bit about the final presentations.
如果我看到什么 我会说 请务必注意
If I see something, I'm like, "Oh, let's make sure
这个在下周四不要发生
that this doesn't happen next Thursday or whatever."
而且在这完成后 如果你计划做一个现场演示
Also, after that's done, if you're planning to do a live demo,
周三将是很好的机会 因为我会设置所有这些
Wednesday will be a great time because I'll have this whole setup here.
你可以连接你的设备
And you can try and hook up your device,
使用我用的这些无线设备
and using this wireless thing that I use,
这个 这让我能够设置起来
and this thing right here -- which let me set that up --
以此展示你的demo 确保它能工作
to show your demo and make sure that it's working,
确保你的设备能行 等等
make sure your device works, all that stuff
这样就能有很好很流畅的demo
so that you can have a nice, smooth demo.
我们会在周三做所有这些
So we'll be doing all that on Wednesday.
周三我不会讲特定主题
Otherwise I'm not going to present a particular topic.
这些事情 我鼓励你们去做
So it's one of those things where, again, I encourage you
我希望你们来听别人的期末陈述
to come be an audience for the people who are doing alternate presentation,
不过这不是强制的
but it's not a mandatory.
当然 最后的所有这些课都不是强制的
I mean, all these lectures at the end here are not mandatory per se.
以上就是周三的情况了
But that's what's going on, on Wednesday.
这方面有问题吗
Any questions about that?
好
All right.
然后周五没有辅导课
And then Friday, no section on Friday.
周五好像是官方期末考试开始的日子
I think it might even be officially start of final exam period on Friday.
我不确定 不过我们没有辅导课
I'm not one hundred percent sure. But in any case, no section.
项目截止时间改成了周日晚上12点
We've moved your project deadline, as you know, to Sunday night at midnight.
提交期末项目时 请一同提交幻灯片
And when you submit your final project, submit your slides.
明天中午12点如果无法上交
Assuming you're not submitting them by noon tomorrow,
周日晚上请务必提交
make sure you submit them by Sunday night.
提交的东西都要放到顶层目录
And just put them right at the top level of whatever you submit.
无论顶层目录在哪 反正就放到那里
Just whatever the top level directory is, just put them there --
Keynote幻灯片这些
Keynote slides.
期末陈述是下周四
The final presentations are a week from Thursday,
也就是分配给这门课的期末考时间 12:15到3:15
so the normally scheduled final exam period for this class, 12:15 to 3:15.
陈述是必需的
The presentation is required.
有人问 是否可选
Some people say, "Is it optional?"
不 这是必需的
No, it's required.
这学期的陈述有2分半钟 这已经很长了
You get two and a half minutes this quarter, which is a long time.
一般我们都只有2分钟
Usually we only give two minutes.
看起来很长 但上去讲你可能就会觉得不够用了
And seems like a long time; when you get up there it will seem short.
重复一次 宽屏纵横比
And again, widescreen aspect ratio.
顺序是随机的
And the order is going to be random.
不要在当天跟我说
You're not going to find out until the day you get it,
也不要发信息跟我说 我要赶飞机
so don't even send me something that I says, "Oh, I got a flight
请让我先讲
to catch, so let me go first."
如果你要赶飞机 那就周三来讲
If you got a flight to catch, then go on Wednesday.
因为出于公平考虑
Go the day after tomorrow because for fairness,
我们打算按事先公布的随机顺序来
I'm going to put it in a random order that will be revealed at the beginning.
这方面有问题吗
Any questions about that?
关于期末项目提交程序和周日晚的截止时间 有问题吗
Any questions about the final project submission process or due date Sunday night?
好 非常棒
Okay. Excellent.
今天的两大主题 一是本地化
So today's two topics, localization --
其实是国际化
really, it's internationalization that I'm going to be talking about --
二是设置
and then settings, which is a UI.
你可以将UI加到设置应用
You can add UI to the settings application
来控制你的程序的特定设置选项
to control certain settings about your application.
然后我要演示两个demo
And the two demos I'm going to do,
我要国际化Photomania
I'm going to internationalize PhotoMania,
我还会对Bouncer添加设置
and I'm going to add a setting to Bouncer.
这两个我都会用demo来演示
That way we'll get both of these things demoed.
好 让我们来讲国际化
All right. So let's talk about internationalization.
国际化实际上有两步
There's really two steps to internationalization:
一个是我们说的国际化
There's something we called "internationalization" --
有时也简称为i18n
sometimes abbreviated I-18-N
因为其中有18个字母 i18n 国际化
because there's 18 letters in there; I-18-N, internationalization --
二是本地化
and then there's localization.
国际化是让app能够本地化的过程
"Internationalization" is the process of making your app possible to be localized.
让app能够以多种语言提供
Making it so that your app can be shipped in multiple different languages.
本地化则是实际翻译的过程
"Localization" is the process of actually translating that --
将应用程序翻译为另一种语言
your application -- to another language.
这是一个两步的过程
So it's really a two-step process.
国际化 这是你作为开发者要做的
Internationalization, that's something you do as the developer.
本地化 这通常需要雇人来做
Localization, usually hire someone to go do that.
我不建议你用谷歌翻译本地化app
I don't recommend using Google Translate to localize your app.
结果会非常奇怪
You get some very strange results.
你需要非常职业的本地化翻译
You want a professional localizer
他们需要理解本地语言的惯用语
who understands the idioms of the local language.
有两点需要本地化
There's really two things that need to be localized:
一是故事板
One is your storyboard and
二是应用中的所有字符串字面量
one is kind of all the literal strings in your application.
我们先来讲故事板
So let's talk about the storyboards first.
在iOS7中本地化故事板
The way we localize storyboards in iOS 7
我们只需要改变故事板中出现的字符串
is we only change the strings that appear in the storyboard,
然后我们再让自动布局来匹配字符串的变宽和变窄
and we let Auto Layout resize things to fit wider and shorter strings.
这是自动布局很方便的一点
That's a great side benefit of having Auto Layout,
这样本地化就只关系到故事板的字符串了
is that localization now is just about the strings when it comes to the storyboard.
不过首先
But the first thing we need
在进行任何本地化之前
to do before we do any localization is to go
我们都需要到项目设置 设置所有语言
to our project settings and set the list of all the languages
所有我们要支持本地化的都要选
that we are going to support localization for.
每次发布新版本程序时
So you know, as you release new versions
你都应该多支持几种语言
of your app, you'll support a few more languages.
你可以到这个项目设定中 添加更多语言
You'll go back to this project settings and add more languages.
关于这个有一点比较巧妙
One thing that's a little tricky about this is
你们原来到项目设置
you're used to going to your project settings,
也就是导航器左上角那部分
which is that upper left-hand top part of the navigator.
一般设置的都是
But actually, what we've been setting the settings of
目标 也就是要创建的app
there is the target, the app that you're building.
这里 你要设置的是项目本身
Here you want to actually set the settings of the project itself.
可以看到蓝色对话框所指的 这里说Photomania
So you can see where that little bubble points to right there that says PhotoMania.
这实际是一个弹窗 你可以点它
That's a little popup actually; you're going to click that
切换到项目的编辑
and switch up to editing the project.
这样做时 整个项目并没有太多设置
And when you do, there's not a whole lot of settings for the whole project.
所有都在这里
You're seeing them all right here.
你只需要到底部
And you're just going to go down to the bottom there.
它说本地化
It says localizations.
这不过是一系列语言
It's just a list of languages.
这些是预支持的语言
These are pre-supported languages
因为这些语言需要匹配
because these languages need to match up with the languages
iOS操作系统所支持的语言
that the operating system, iOS, supports
当用户到设置或是其它程序
so that when people go to settings and other apps,
语言也都会是这些
that's in whatever language as well.
点击左下角的+按钮
So when you hit that little plus button down in the lower left-hand corner,
一系列语言会弹出
it's going to be a popup with a list of languages.
你不需要键入阿拉伯语或是法语
You're not going to just type in the word Arabic or French;
你可以从iOS支持的语言中来选
it's going to be something you're going to pick from a list
of supported languages for iOS.
还可以看到
And you can also see
这里有个语言称作base(基础)
that there's a language there called base, right?
还有一个开关说 使用base国际化
And there's a switch that says use base internationalization.
base国际化的概念是说
The concept of base internationalization is
这里会有一个本地化
that there's going to be a localization.
这不是任何语言的本地化 而是base本地化
It's not a localization that is in anybody's language; it's just the base localization.
这就像是所有的默认值
And that's going to be kind of like all the defaults:
默认故事板字符串
The default storyboard strings,
app中的默认字符串 会来自于base本地化
default strings throughout your app are going to come out of the base localization.
然后其它这些本地化
And then all these other localizations,
甚至英语 然后还有法语 德语这些
like English even, but French, and German, and whatever,
这些会修改这些字符串
those are going to modify those strings.
如果你忘了本地化一个字符串
And so if you forget to localize a string,
base本地化就会接手
the base localization will shine through.
等下我们会看到故事板中这是怎样的情况
And so we'll see what that looks like when it comes to storyboards in a second here.
故事板是这样的
So the storyboards look like this.
你选择一个故事板
You select a storyboard.
如果你做了我上一张幻灯片中所示的事情
And when you do the thing I showed you on the previous slide,
那么你的故事板在文件浏览器中就会像这样
then your storyboards are going to look like this in the file navigator.
看到这里有主iPhone故事板了吗
You see how there's main, iPhone, storyboard?
这里你有一个小三角可以点
And now it has a little triangle that you can click
它下面还是显示有主iPhone故事板 base
and it now is showing underneath it main, iPhone, storyboard again -- base.
这是base故事板
So that's your base storyboard.
然后对于法语 它说主iPhone 点字符串
And then for French, it says main, iPhone, dot strings.
这里只是故事板中的字符串被提取了
So that's just the strings only for the storyboards that have been extracted.
做了前面那件事 这个就会被提取出来
When we did that previous thing, it extracted those out there.
点故事板 到文件检查器
And when you click on the storyboard and if you go to the file inspector,
你就能看到这个显示在那里
you can see this little thing showing there
有base 这是总有的
where there's base -- there will always be base --
然后是你想翻译成的任意多种语言
and then however many languages you want to translate to.
注意到这里 英语甚至没有勾选
Now, here notice that English is not even checked;
这是因为我将假定我的base是英语
that's because I'm going to assume that my base is English.
你并不需要总是这样假定
Now, you don't always want to assume that.
你甚至大多数时候都可以假定
And you could even mostly assume that
还是有一个英语点字符串文件
but still have an English dot strings file
在需要的时候改变一些东西
that changed a couple of things if you wanted.
或者你可以让这整个东西
Or you could have the whole thing be, you know,
用英文字符串文件明言出来
explicitly in a strings file for English.
但这里我没有勾选英文
But here I have not even checked English.
base故事板中的东西
So whatever's in my base storyboard, that's what's going
就是语言为英文时的情况
to ship when I'm in the language English.
不过法语中 我有一个可本地化的字符串文件
But in French I have a localizable without strings file,
马上我就会展示
which I'll show you in a second,
这会改变故事板中的所有字符串
which is going to change all the strings in my storyboard.
法语语言字符串是怎样的呢
So what does that look like? The French language strings?
这部分内容将推迟一些
I'm going to postpone showing what that looks
我们将先笼统地讨论字符串
like until we talk about strings in general.
我们来看字符串字面量
And so let's talk about literal strings.
故事板的那些将是
So the storyboard strings are going to be
我在刚才那张幻灯片中讲的
in this thing I showed you in the last slide.
不过app中还有一些字符串不在故事板中
But there's other strings inside your app that aren't in the storyboard,
例如警告消息中的字符串 警告按钮
like things that come up in alert messages, the alert buttons.
所有这些都不在故事板中 但也需要本地化
All those things are not in your storyboard, but they need be localized as well.
我们让这些字符串得到本地化的方式
And the way we get those strings to be localizable
是使用这些以NSLocalizedString开头的宏
is using these macros here that start with NS localized string.
这里有NSLocalizedStringWithDefaultValue
So there's NS localized string with default value;
有NSLocalizedStringFromTable
there's NS localized string from table;
有NSLocalizedString
there's NS localized string.
这些宏的参数都略有不同
And each of these macros takes a little bit different arguments.
它们的主要作用是给你一个键
But the main thing they're doing is you're giving a key that's
到字符串去查找 会返回一个值
going to be looked up in a strings file and it's going to return a value.
版本有多种是因为
The different variants just determine:
不能找到字符串时的默认值会不同
What's the default value if I can't find the thing in the string,
在哪些点字符串文件中找也会不同
and which dot strings file am I going to look in?
对于故事板 总是只关联有一个字符串文件
Okay, for our storyboard there's always one string file associated.
但对于代码中的字符串字面量
But when we have literal strings inside of our code, we can
我们可以把翻译拆分到不同的文件中
split up all the translations into different files if we want.
demo中我会这样做
In the demo I'll do that.
我会把它们放到一个单独的小文件中
I'll put them in a little separate file
只针对一个视图控制器
just for one view controller.
例如 如果你有字符串字面量 hello
So for example, if you had the literal string hello,
@号 引号 hello在app中
at sign, quote, hello in your app
而这会出现在UI中 那么
and that is going to appear in the UI, then you would change
你就要把它变为NSLocalizedString
that to NS localized string
@ hello 逗号
at hello comma.
之后 最后一个参数是给本地化者的注释
And then, the last argument there is a comment to the localizers.
你可以假定本地化者说你的语言 你的base语言
So you can assume the localizers speak your language, whatever your base language is,
你给他们一个注释
and you're giving them a comment.
告诉他们这个hello是什么
You're telling them what is this hello?
它在什么环境中出现
Where does it appear? What's its environment?
这里我说 它是应用开始时的寒暄
So here I'm saying it's a greeting at the start of the application.
那么讲法语的人就会把这翻译成bonjour
So the person would know in French to make that be bonjour or whatever.
这就是将所有字符串字面量
Right? So that's how you change all your literal strings
转化为NSLocalizedString的方式
to these NS localized string, one of these variants.
这些NSLocalizedString是做什么的呢
Now what are these things actually doing, these NS localized string?
它们会在NSBundle中调用一个方法
They're actually calling a method in NS bundle.
NSBundle是一个类
NS bundle is a class
它会将你app里的一切收集起来
that kind of collects everything about your app,
到一个API中 用于访问其资源
okay, into an API for accessing the resources of it.
我们可以用它来访问字符串文件
And we can use it to access strings files,
做法是使用Bundle中的这个方法
and we do that with this method in bundle
也就是localizedStringForKey value table
called localized string for key value table, right?
顾名思义 key是用于在字符串文件中查找的键
Exactly what you would think: Key is what we're looking up in the strings files;
value是这里的默认值
value is the default value there;
table是在哪个表格中查询
and table is which table to look in.
顺便说下 Bundle还可以被用于查找资源的URL
The bundle can also be used, by the way, to find URLs
资源诸如图像等等
to resources like images, things like that.
如果你拖动一张jpeg图像
If you drag an image -- a JPEG image --
到导航器的顶层
right into the top level of your navigator,
那你就可以使用NSBundle mainBundle
then you can use NS bundle main bundle.
这里有URLForResource
There's something called URL for resource,
你给它jpeg文件的名称
and you give it the name of that JPEG file.
它会告诉你相应的URL
It will give you a URL to it.
有时 你需要某张图像的完整URL
Sometimes you need a full URL to some image.
如果你不使用图像名 你会使用完整URL
Or if you're not using image named, you need some full URL.
NSBundle就是这样一个类 需要你有所理解
So NS bundle is a class for you to kind of understand a little bit as well.
有时 我们会调用这个localizedStringForKey
But we don't usually -- well, sometimes we'll call this localized string for key,
demo中我也会这样做
and I'll do it in the demo as well. But
可以用这些宏时 我们就应当使用
when we can use the macros, we should.
不过NSLocalizedString中的宏有很大的局限性
But there's a significant limitation on those macros, the NS localized string:
所有的字符串都必须是字符串字面量
All the arguments have to be literal strings,
包括评论 键 值
including the comment; the key; the value;
表名 等等 这里不能是变量
the table name; etc. They can't be variables.
必然是字符串字面量
They have to be literal strings.
@号引号什么 @号引号什么
At sign quote something, at sign quote something
LocalizedString的每个参数都是如此
for every argument of those localized strings.
我们来谈谈为什么是这样
And then let's talk about why that is.
答案是有一个命令行实用程序叫作
The answer for that is there's a command line utility called
genstrings
genstrings --
生成字符串的简写
short for generate strings --
它会找遍整个.m文件
which will look through a dot M file
找所有LocalizedString宏
for all those NS localized string macros
并将它们提取到一个字符串文件
and extract them all out into a strings file for you.
这就是你得到base字符串文件的方式
And that's how you get the base string file
然后你再本地化到其它语言
that you will then localize to other languages.
我们也会在demo中演示这个
And we'll show this in the demo as well.
例如 我们有NSLocalizedString @号 hello
And so, for example, we had that NS localized string at sign hello,
应用开始时的寒暄
greeting at start of application.
这会在字符串文件中转化为下面那两行
That would get turned into the following two lines there in a strings file:
注释 应用开始时的寒暄
Comment, greeting is started by application,
然后 hello等于hello
and then hello equals hello.
法国人看到这个
And the French person would come along
可以将其改成hello等于bonjour
and they would change hello equals bonjour.
执行genstrings
Now, when you do genstrings
会生成得到.strings文件
and you get dot strings files generated --
你会得到多个这样的文件
and you might get multiple of them because remember,
因为NSLocalizedString的一个方法就是
one of the NS localized strings is
NSLocalizedStringFromTable
NS localized string from table,
你需要指定表名
so you might specify table name.
这会为你生成多个.strings文件
And so it might be making multiple dot strings files for you.
你只需要将这些.strings文件
You just take those dot strings files,
拖入到应用程序 到Xcode项目中
drag them into your application, into your Xcode project,
然后打开文件检查器检查它们
and then inspect them with a file inspector.
这时你可以看到这个按钮
And when you do, you're going to see this button,
上面那个按钮 它说本地化
the top button there that says localize.
点这个 你会得到一系列语言的列表
And when you click that, then you'll get a list of the languages.
你可以勾选任意多种语言
And you can click however many of the languages you want
来支持这个字符串文件的本地化
to support localizing this string file for.
然后在文件浏览器中
And then in your file navigator
你会看到每种语言都有一个.strings文件
you'll see a dot strings file for every language.
点开它
You can click on it.
通常你会看到
And then you -- usually what you'll do is you'll click on it
hello等于hello
and you'll see hello equal hello.
然后你把所有.strings文件
You'll take that entire file or all the strings files,
交给本地化者
ship them off to a localizer --
或许还连同app的demo一起
maybe with a demo of your app or something like that --
他们会翻译所有这些字符串并发送回来
they'll translate all the strings and send them back.
你把这些放入到Xcode项目中 就可以交付了
And then you just plop them into your Xcode project and ship it.
这些Bundle的排列方式是这样的
So the way that these bundles are arranged is inside a
你的应用程序是主Bundle
bundle -- and your application is the main bundle,
这会在应用程序的顶层
so that's the top level of your application --
其中是这些lproj目录
inside are these lproj directories.
lproj目录的名称
And the name of the lproj directory is
会是两个字母的语言表示
like a little two-letter symbol for the language.
例如en.lproj 这是英语
So there's EN dot lproj; that's English.
fr.lproj 这是法语
There's FR dot lproj; that's French.
lproj中是所有的字符串文件 用于语言本地化
And inside the lproj is all the strings files for localizing to that language.
就这么简单
It's as simple as that.
如果你支持25种语言 你就会有25个.lproj文件
So you might have, you know, 25 dot lprojs if you support 25 languages.
每个里面 都会有要编辑的字符串文件副本
In all them there will be a copy of the strings files that are edited.
你们还可以离线去查更多NSBundle方面的信息
You can look more about NS bundle offline,
不过字符串文件不仅仅能够关联到
but there are ways to also associate strings files not just
app的主Bundle
with your main bundle of your app,
它还可以关联到框架这些
but if you had a framework or something else, you could associate it with frameworks
因为Bundle除了mainBundle
because bundle, in addition to main bundle,
还有这个bundleForClass方法
it has this bundle for class method.
它知道这个类来自哪里
And so it knows where that class came from,
是框架还是主Bundle
whether it was a framework or your main bundle.
它会给你Bundle 然后你会得到一个路径
And it will give you the bundle, and then you can get a path
对应资源 或是使用localizedStringForKey value table
for a resource or do localized string for key value table.
好 关于本地化调试简单讲两点
Okay. Couple of things about debugging localization.
有一个很好的用户默认你可以设置
There's a really nice user default that you can set,
NSShowNonLocalizedStrings
NS show non-localized strings.
这些NSLocalizedString…
And every time one of those NS localized string --
我说方法 其实是宏
I say methods, but really they're macros --
只要这些宏不能在字符串文件中找到条目
any time one of those does not find an entry in a string file,
你就会得到一个log
you'll get a little log.
这时你就知道本地化遗漏了一条
So then you'll know that your localizer missed one.
知道这个很重要
Okay. So that's important to know.
当你在就本地化进行质量评价时
So that way when you're doing your QA of your localizations
你要保证这些能够正常工作
to make sure that they're really working as good.
我看到过有人抱怨
I've seen some people complain
有时他们添加一些.strings文件到本地化
that sometimes they'll add some strings to a localization
测试时会报错说新变化不存在
and test it and it's like, "Oh, it's not getting the new changes."
我还没在iOS7中碰到过这种情况
I haven't seen that in iOS 7,
如果你碰到了 尝试清除项目
but if you do, building clean
重新安装似乎能够解决这个问题
and reinstalling seems to solve that problem.
我不知道这种情况什么时候会发生
I don't know exactly the circumstances that supposedly happens under,
不过清除项目总是值得尝试
but it can't hurt to build clean.
以上是字符串
Okay. So that's strings.
所有这些我都会在demo中演示
And we'll see all this happening in the demo.
很不幸的是 本地化还不仅仅是字符串这么简单
There's more to localization, though, than just strings unfortunately.
这里还有locale(语言区域)的概念
There's also the concept of a locale.
用户不仅可能使用不同语言
So your user not only might speak a different language,
还有可能有不同的locale
they might live in any number of different locales.
英语是个很好的例子
An easy one to think about is English.
美国人说英语
In America we speak English.
英国人也说英语
In Great Britain they speak English.
但当地惯用语 货币表示都不一样
But there are local idioms and the way that we express currency,
还有大数字表示
the way we even just express numbers -- big numbers --
例如逗号和句号被交换了
the commas and the periods are swapped, for example.
一切都略有不同
Things just are all slightly different.
虽然两个国家的语言都是英语
So even though language in both of those countries would be English,
但locale不同
the locales would be different.
这里对于locale 有另外一个系统
So there's a whole other system here for locales.
用户用设置app
And users set their language
设定语言和locale
and their locale using the settings app.
你的应用则会作出适应
And your application it's just supposed to adapt.
这需要通过一些将locale作为参数的方法
And you adapt by using some of these methods that take a locale as an argument
或是使用locale的方法
or that use a locale under the covers.
你可以用这些方法知道当前locale是什么
You can find out what current locale is with these methods,
还有这个很棒的autoupdatingCurrentLocale
and you can also have this nice autoupdating current locale,
如果用户更改了locale
which if the user changes their locale,
它会自动替你进行更新
it will just automatically update underneath the covers;
只是你可能需要监听这个广播站
although, you probably want to listen to this radio station,
因为发生变化时 你可能需要重新绘制UI
too, because if it changes, you might have to redraw your UI. Right? If they change?
用户一般不会在程序运行时
But it's pretty unusual for the user to change their locale
更改locale或语言 不过这可能发生
or their language while they're in the middle of running your app, but it could happen.
你需要防患于未然
Okay. You should be prepared for that to happen.
locale中有些什么不同呢
So what are some of the things that are different in a locale?
这里涉及到数字
Well, there's numbers.
数字格式方面这里有很多东西
Now, there's a lot going on with formatting numbers.
你可能会以为很简单
It seems like it's really simple,
但这里有很多要考虑的东西
but there's actually a lot to think about here.
我打算讲两个很简单的例子
But I'm going to look at two pretty simple cases.
一个是显示数字 另一个是读取数字
One is displaying numbers and one is reading numbers.
对于在屏幕上显示数字 你可能希望
So for displaying number on screen you're probably want
使用stringWithFormat %g
to do string with format percent G.
%g是说通用浮点数
"Percent G" just means generic floating point number.
但这里不要这样
But you don't want to do that.
你需要使用NSNumberFormatter中的这个方法
What you want to do is use this method in NS number formatter
名为localizedStringFromNumber numberStyle
called localized string from number, number style.
数字样式有很多 例如小数 还有拼出
Okay. And there's different number styles like decimal and spell out.
拼出是说 例如4 我们要拼成four
We'll even spell it out. Like, if you put a four in there, it will say four, f-o-u-r.
这是拼出
Okay, spell it out.
这里有不同的格式
So there's different formats for doing that.
这会返回一个可以放到UI中的字符串
And that will give you back a string that you can put in the UI
显示数字的方式将适用于你所处的locale
that will display the number in a way that's appropriate for the locale you're in.
对于大数字 例如1000
And especially, again, a large number like a thousand
美国会写成1,000.00
in the US might be one comma zero zero zero point zero zero;
而英国会写成1.000,00
whereas in Great Britain it would be one period zero zero zero comma zero zero.
这样做就能弄对那些
Okay. And so this would get that right.
然后有解析数字 读取数字
Then there's parsing numbers, reading them.
这里你可能想说int value
You really probably want here to just say int value
或是字符串的float value
or float value of a string,
这会将浮点数或是整型数解释为输入
which will parse it and try it interpret a float or an int as the input.
但这并不是正确的做法
But that's not really the right way to do it.
你应该使用NumberFormatter
You should use the number formatter here.
你创建一个formatter
So you just create a formatter,
设置你要读取数字的样式
set the style of number that you're trying to read in --
同上面一样
same thing as we saw above there --
然后你将得到解析后的数字 作为NSNumber
and then you're going to get the parsed number as in NS number
通过调用numberFromString
by calling number from string.
这会去看那个字符串
And that's going to look in that string,
然后把它解析为货币或是小数
parse it like a currency or just a decimal number.
如果用户键入1.000,00
And so if the person types in one period zero zero zero comma zero zero,
而他处在英国locale 你就会得到1000
you'll get a thousand if they're in the Great Britain locale.
理解吗
Make sense?
而在美国 你就无法得到
Whereas in the US you wouldn't get that.
1.000可能让你得到1 甚至nil
One period zero zero zero probably will give you one or might even give you nil
因为这甚至不是合法的数字
because that's not really even a number.
日期 这个也很复杂 你需要小心
Dates -- another complicated one you have to be careful of.
关于日期 我只想说
All I'm going to say about dates is
记住我们所使用的公历
familiarize yourself with the concept that our calendar,
并不是世界上唯一的历法
the Gregorian calendar, is not the only calendar in the world.
历法还有别的
There are other calendars out there.
iOS中有处理所有这些的机制
And there's mechanism in iOS for dealing with all of them,
不过你需要知道怎么做 我显然没时间一一讲到
but you have to know how to do it. I can't cover it all in one lecture --
我就算用一堂课讲 也不见得讲得完
even if I had a whole lecture devoted to it probably.
不过你们可以看看NSCalendar这些类
But you want to look at classes like NS calendar,
看看其说明文档 去熟悉一下
search through the documentation. Kind of familiarize yourself.
如果你要让应用程序具有多语言
If you're really going to do a multi-language,
多locale 而日期是你UI的一部分
multi-locale application, and dates are part of your UI,
你就需要理解这里是怎么回事
you really want to understand what you're doing there.
对于简单日期的格式化 这里有一个很棒的方法
For formatting simple dates there's this nice method,
localizedStringFromDate 带有dateStyle
localize string from date with the date style.
使用这个 你就能完成很多事情
You can get away with a lot by just using this one.
不过如果你要对日期做更复杂的事
But if you're doing anything more complicated with dates
例如你写的是日历app
like you're writing the calendar app or something,
那么你显然就需要更好地理解日期
then you obviously want to really understand dates better.
字符串 这里很有趣 如果你在字符串中搜索
Strings, an interesting thing: If you're searching in a string,
特别是区分大小写的搜索
okay, especially if you're searching case insensitively
想找到字符串中的一个单词
to try and find a word in a string,
不要使用一般的rangeOfString方法
you don't want to use the range of string method;
你要用这个rangeOfString方法
you want to use this range of string method --
rangeOfString range locale
range of string options range locale --
传递给它当前locale
and pass the current locale.
区分大小写和变音符号的情况尤是如此
And this is especially true with case insensitivity and when diacritics are involved
因为不同语言对变音符号的处理是不同的
because different languages treat the diacritics differently.
不同语言对区分大小写的处理也是不同的
And case sensitivity is different in different languages.
这里你显然需要使用这个方法
So you would definitely want to use this method for that.
UIImage很有趣
UI image is kind of an interesting one.
想想你在写一个app 例如一个驾车app
What if you were writing an app, some kind of driving app
你有一个停止标志
or something like that and you have a stop sign?
停止标志在几乎所有locale都是相同的
The stop sign is pretty much the same in almost all locales.
这就很好了
So you're good to go.
但其它标志 例如让路标志 可能会非常不同
But other signs, like yield signs and things like that, can be quite different
在其locale 用户可能会不认识你的让路标志
and your user wouldn't even recognize a yield sign in their locale.
你需要用不同的图像 让图像也能本地化
You might want to have a different image and have the image be localizable.
做起来很简单
Really easy to do.
对于每个locale 你只需要将图像放到其lproj中…
You just put the image for each locale, you know, in its lproj --
抱歉 对于语言 放到lproj中
sorry -- for the languages in its lproj
然后你将它提出
and then you pull it out.
不过哪怕这里 如果语言还有不同的locale
But even there, if you have a language that might have different locales
不同的标志会有相同的语言在它上面
that have a different sign with the same language on it,
有趣的是 停止在很多语言中都是一样的
amazingly stop is "stop" in most languages,
哪怕stop不是法语中的单词
even though "stop" is obviously not a word in French.
你去法国 你看到停止标志说stop
If you go to France, you'll see stop signs that say "stop,"
这有些奇怪
which is kind of strange.
不过可能 不同locale的情况会有不同
But there might be locales where things are different,
这样就需要在UIImage imageNamed上做些额外工作
so you might have to do a little extra work on top of UI image image named.
你可能需要说 如果我在这个locale 它就应该是这样
You might have to say, "Oh, if I'm in this locale, then it looks like this."
这只发生在应用中会有路标这样的图像时
Now, again, that's only if you're doing an application that has imagery like road signs
这些东西非常具有locale特异性
or whatever that's very locale-specific.
这方面本地化者可能也会帮助你
That's something a localizer will hopefully help you.
你放上一个让路标志
You'll put a yield sign up, and they'll say, "Oh,
他们可能会说 瑞典的路标不一样
wait a second in" -- you know, I don't know -- "Sweden that looks different."
或是 阿富汗是这样的
Or, you know, "In Afghanistan it's this."
本地化者可能会帮助你
And so your localizers will hopefully help you.
不过UIImage imageNamed
But UI image, image named
会在lproj中为你找
will look in the lprojs for you.
这上面可能还需要locale
You might still have to locale on top of that.
这里我们要做的demo是
So the demo we're going to do here is
国际化Photomania
internationalizing PhotoMania.
我将打开上周那堂课我们最后得到的Photomania
So I'm going to start with the PhotoMania that we had at our last lecture, last week.
这是Photomania
So here's PhotoMania.
看Photomania这里的UI
And PhotoMania is UI here.
很美妙 它其实很容易本地化
It's amazing, it's actually pretty easy to localize
因为Photomania显示的主要是内容
because PhotoMania, primarily what it displays is its content.
看看所有这些UI你会发现
Right? If you look at almost all of this UI,
它不过是显示从Flickr取回的数据
it's just only displaying what's coming back from Flickr.
其中很少再有别的文字了
It hardly has any other text in it.
这是很好的UI设计
That's actually very good UI design.
一般而言 你希望UI中尽量高百分比的
Generally, you want as high a percentage of the UI
都是你要显示的
to be what you're displaying --
如果你是照片观赏app
so if you're photo viewing app,
你希望到处都是照片 只在边上有少量控制元件
you would want photo everywhere and just a little bit of controls around the edges.
不过还是有些地方
But there is a couple of places.
你可以看到这个 这里有不少字符串
You can see this guy right here has quite a few strings in it right there.
此外还有各种字符串出现在
And there's some miscellaneous strings that we load up as part
这些原型单元格中 这是需要可本地化的
of these prototype cells that might need to be localizable.
我们先从添加具有其它这些语言的能力开始
But let's start, like I said, with adding the ability to have these other languages.
做法是点这里来编辑我们的项目
And we do that by clicking here to edit our project.
重申一次 我们要编辑的不是目标 而是这个
But again, we don't want to be editing the target; we want to edit this.
这是这里
So this is something right here.
不要忘记这一步
Don't forget this step right here.
我们要的是项目
We want the project.
这样做之后 你会看到本地化
And when we do that, now you'll see there's localization.
下面这里是本地化
Here's the localizations down here.
我们要使用base本地化
And we are going to use base localization,
这意味着故事板将是我们的base
which means our storyboard is going to be our base
之后我们会修改这些字符串
and we're going to modify the strings after that.
我要添加法语
So I'm going to add French.
让我们添加法语
So let's add French.
它问我
It's asking me,
已有的东西里面 你要为哪些创建.strings文件
"What existing stuff do you want to make strings files for?"
我要所有这些 故事板的所有这些
And I'm just going to say all of it, all my storyboards
不要太担心InfoPlist.strings
and don't worry too much about info P list dot strings.
这里只有少许需要本地化
There's a little bit in there to localize,
例如app名可以本地化
like your app name can actually be localized.
不过主要是在故事板中
But most of your stuff is in your storyboard.
这里两个故事板都选上
So we'll have both storyboards.
这样做时 它会添加法语
And when we do that, it just adds French here.
我们可以看看这个
And if we look up here, look at this.
这里有个小三角 点它
Now this has a little triangle that, if we click it,
我们就能看到这里有base故事板
we get to see that there's the base storyboard
然后是法语的.strings文件
and now there's string files for French.
.strings文件就是这样的
So here's what a strings file looks like.
它有给本地化者的注释 然后是一个键 然后是一个值
It's got a comment to the localizer, and then a key, and then a value.
这里的这些键
Now, these keys right here,
我们怎么知道什么匹配什么
how do we know what matches up with what?
多数时候 我们可以看值 例如done
Well, most of the time we can look at the value like done.
我们知道done是这个完成按钮 很容易
Well, we know that done is this done button -- easy.
但看title
But look at title.
这里有三个title
See, there's two, three titles.
这里有一个 这里有两个
There's a title right here and there's two title right here.
哪个标题是哪个呢
It's like which title is which?
这是哪个
Which is this?
这个title又是哪个
And which is this title right here, for example?
你可以点这些title来看
And you can find that out by clicking on any of the titles.
例如点这个
Like, let's click on this one
这个我们显然需要本地化
because we do definitely want to localize this one.
到检查器中 到身份检查器 这是其身份的一部分
Go over to the inspector, go to the identity inspector -- it's part of its identity --
可以看到所有对象在故事板中都有对象ID
and you can see that all objects have an object ID in a storyboard.
看到了吗
You see that?
这个是65e-yS-HIT
So this one's 65EYS hit.
也就是这个
So that is this one.
这个就对应于之前的那个title了
So this one is the title that is the title of that.
另外这两个title 我们甚至不需要本地化它们
Now, these other two titles, we don't even need to localize them
因为它们在这些原型中
because they are in these prototypes here.
这两个原型 它们不会出现在UI上
These two prototypes, so they never appear on the UI, right,
这些title和subtitle
these titles and subtitles. We always
因为我们总会用表格视图中的数据来填充它们
drive them with whatever our data source is for our table view.
不过这个我们需要本地化
But this one we do need to localize,
然后这个subtitle也是 它是qcj
and then also this little subtitle one here, too, which is QCJ.
它也需要本地化
This one also needs to be localized.
怎样本地化呢
So what does it look like to localize these?
假设我是一个本地化者 在本地化它
Let's say I'm a localizer and I'm localizing it.
很不幸 我没有掌握本地化它所需的法语
Unfortunately, I don't quite know enough French to localize this.
我要给你们展示一个很酷的本地化方式
So I'm going to show you a kind of cool way to localize --
这对于测试很有帮助 也就是放一个句点
which is good for testing -- which is just to put a period
在每个字母之间 像这样
between every letter like that.
作为开发者像这样进行本地化会很方便
So do a localization like this as a developer because it's easy for you to do.
你不需要懂那门语言
You don't have to know the language.
而且很酷的是 这会让一切都变宽
And what's cool about this is it makes everything wide.
这会挑战你的UI
So it's going to really challenge your UI
让其在字符串变更时能够匹配宽度
to make things fit when you change these strings, right?
这甚至能够对德语奏效 要知道德语单词都很长
It might even work for German if you do this because German tends to be very long words.
而且 你可以很快地这样做
And it's also, again, really -- you can do it really quickly.
让我们这样来本地化这整个文件
Let's go ahead and localize this entire file by doing this.
关于这个还有一点好处也就是
And another good thing about this is
UI中这个出现的任何位置
everywhere in the UI that this appears,
马上都会非常明显
it's going to be really obvious immediately.
糟糕 我忘了这个
Oops. I forgot that one, right?
因为句点在UI中很容易看到
Because this period's very, very easy to see in the UI.
这两个title和这个subtitle我们不需要管
So we don't need to do these two titles or this subtitle.
这个也不需要管 因为这是占位符
We don't need to do this because that's just a placeholder.
不过下面这个subtitle要处理
We want this subtitle down here, though,
因为这是另一个subtitle
because that's the other subtitle.
这个也一样
We want this one, too.
然后是这个URL
And so the little URL guy here.
还有cancel
And cancel.
这样就本地化了所有
So we've localized this entire thing,
需要本地化为法语的东西
everything that needs to be localized to French.
将文件发送给本地化者时 这些也可以删掉
When you send this off to the localizer you might even take these things out of here.
这样对于哪些该翻译 本地化者就不会感到困扰了
So the localizer on this one, too. The localizer doesn't even get confused,
you know, like, what's going on.
不过有些参数需要留着
However, there's some arguments to leave them in
因为你要使用NSShowNonLocalizedStrings
because you're going to put that little NS show non-localized strings --
用户默认 我讲过的
the user default I talked about --
你可能会对所有这些抱怨很多
on, and then you're going to complaint about all these ones.
这里有大概6个 如果你要这样做的话
So its kinda, 6 in one hand, half dozen in the other, if you want to do that.
好 现在我们本地化了这个
All right. So now we've localized this.
结果会是怎样呢 我们运行着试试
What does it look like? So let's run this and see.
好 运行这个UI时 它都是英文
All right. So when we run this UI, it all looks like it's in English, right?
点击这里的添加照片按钮
And in fact, if we go over to our little add photo guy right
这些都是英语 一切正常
here, this all looks to be English and everything looks fine.
没有任何东西变化了 因为我们没调成法语
Nothing has changed because we're not running in French.
这里还是英语
We're still running in English.
显示的都还是base故事板
So the base storyboard is still showing through.
这很好
Okay, that's good.
检查很必要
That's a good thing to check,
确保没有在本地化过程中破坏什么东西
to make sure you haven't broken anything by adding a localization.
下面我们将语言换成法语
But now let's go and change the language to be French.
这可以在模拟器中进行 也可以在设备上进行
So you do that, you can do it in the simulator and you can do it on your device.
到通用 国际 语言 我们选法语
And you just go here to general, international, language -- we'll change it to French.
现在语言变更了
Okay. It's changing the language.
你的应用如果现在在运行
Your application, if it was running right now,
会得到我们谈到过的通知说
would get that notification that we talked about that says,
哦 这个变了
"Oh, this has changed."
你可以重新绘制你的UI
So you could redraw your UI.
我们回到这里来运行 看看会得到什么
But let's go back and run here and see what we get.
这是拍照者
So here's photographer.
但愿这里能够填入正确的数据
Hopefully this is going to fill in with its normal data.
没问题
Yes, it does.
再到这里 看这个
Let's go over here and look here.
可以看到这里加的点都显示了出来
And you can see that it has done our little dot language here.
我们切换到了法语 这里都加了点
We switched it to French and it's done our little dot language,
但我们什么都读不到 因为宽度超了
but we can't really read everything because nothing fits, right?
副标题和标题都超了
Subtitle doesn't fit, title.
宽度无法匹配 这就是加点的一个好处
So this is good that it doesn't fit, and this is part of the advantage of doing the dots.
还注意到这个
Also notice this.
这还是英语 这不好 让我们修正这些
This is all still in English. So that's no good. So let's fix these things.
宽度不匹配很好解决
The things not fitting is quite easy to fix.
我们只需要到这里的故事板
We're just going to go to the storyboard right here,
重置为使用自动布局
and I'm going to reset to use Auto Layout.
把所有这些拖入时
Okay. Now when I dragged all these things in,
我相信我使用了蓝线
I believe I used the blue lines.
在重置为建议约束条件时
So when I reset to suggested constraints,
建议约束条件应该就能工作
I think I'm going to get suggested constraints that work.
让我们来看看
So let's go ahead and take a look.
现在就可以看到 这些宽度都匹配好了
Enter enough and you can see now all these things fit.
看到了吗 cancel done title都好了
See that? Cancel fits, done, title.
自动布局把一切都办得很好
So we did a good job with our Auto Layout.
自动布局是本地化的一个基本组成部分
So Auto Layout is a fundamental part of localization.
很基本
Fundamental.
如果自动布局没有设对 本地化就无从谈起
If you don't have your Auto Layout right, you cannot do localization
因为字符串变化时
because when you change the strings,
到处都会被切断 都是... 所有这些糟糕的东西
everything will be cut off, and dot dot dot, and all this bad stuff.
那这里的英语呢
But what about this English right here?
这个我们也需要改成法语
We got to fix this, we got to get rid of this.
这些都不在故事板中
And these are actually not in my storyboard.
这些字符串 例如OK 还有Add Photo
These strings, like "Okay," and "Add photo,"
还有Sorry, this device cannot add a photo
and "Sorry, this device cannot add a photo,"
这些都是代码中的字符串字面量
those are all literal strings in my code.
让我们来本地化它们
So let's go localize those.
这些都是我们上周加的代码
And those are all in the thing we added last week.
但愿你们记得这些 也就是AddPhotoViewController
So hopefully you remember some of this code, which is add photo view controller.
这是AddPhotoViewController
So here's add photo view controller.
这里在我实现的任何东西中
So one thing I like to do in anything that I implement
我都可以搜索@号引号
is search for at sign quote.
因为@号引号就意味着字符串字面量
Because at sign quote is going to be literal strings.
并非所有字符串字面量都需要本地化
Now, not all literal strings need to be localized.
但这个 这个 这个和这个需要本地化
But like, this one does, and this one, and this one, and this one.
这个不需要 这是segue标识符
This one not; this is a segue identifier.
不会出现在UI中 不需要本地化
Never appears in the UI. Does not need to be localized.
这个也不需要 这是数据库中实体的名称
This one also not; this is the name of an entity in the database --
至少这里我们不会放到UI中
or at least in this case we don't put this in the UI,
虽然在UI的其它地方可能需要本地化
although we do somewhere else in the UI.
对未来做什么可能会有一个预览
A little preview of what we're going to do later.
当然 所有这些都需要本地化
And then, of course, all of these need to be localized, right?
这个也需要
This one also.
这些东西都是警告用的
All these things do is alerts.
这个不需要 这是缩略图
This one not; this is thumbnail.
这是文件扩展名
This is just a little file extension
用于缩略图URL 不会出现在UI中
for our thumbnail URL -- never appears in the UI.
这个也不会出现在UI中
Here's another one that never appears the UI.
这就是我们创建独特文档URL的方式
This is how we're making a unique document URL.
这里我们不需要使用NumberFormatter这些
So here we don't need to use a number formatter and all that business.
然后这里滤镜中还有一些
And then here's some more of the filter stuff.
注意到滤镜中 这个需要本地化 这个则不需要
Notice in the filter stuff this does not need to be localized, but this does.
这个会出现在动作表单 这个只用于幕后的代码
This appears in the action sheet; this is just used in the code behind the scenes.
因此我们只需要本地化chrome blur noir和fade
So we only have to do these chrome, blur, noir, and fade.
以上就是需要本地化的东西
So that's the stuff that needs to be localized.
如何本地化呢
So how are we going to localize that?
让我们选一个
Let's pick one of these.
选这个如何
How about let's pick this one right here:
Sorry, this device cannot add a photo.
"Sorry, this device cannot add a photo."
因为我们知道这个立马就会出现
Because we know that's going to come up right away.
如何本地化这个呢
So how would we localize this?
这部分涉及到编程艺术
Some of this is art of programming;
部分涉及到怎样才能有效工作
some of it is kind of what's a way that's really going to work effectively?
我认为这里最佳的做法之一是
But I think one of the best ways to do this is to get rid
将字符串字面量用#号定义取代
of this literal string and replace it with something you pound sign define.
这个我打算称作ALERT_CANT_ADD_PHOTO
So I'm going to call this one "Alert can't add photo."
这里我还要加些注释 把这个粘贴回来
And I'm actually going to put a little comment here and paste that thing back
这样我就记得我原来想用英语说什么了
so I can remember what I originally intended to say in English.
然后我要添加一个#号定义
And then I'm going to add a pound sign define
用于这个警告 ALERT_CANT_ADD_PHOTO
for this alert, can't add photo
这是一个NSLocalizedString
that's an NS localized string --
那个宏 NSLocalizedString
that macro NS localized string.
实际上是NSLocalizedStringFromTable
In fact, NS localized string from table.
我打算把这些放到我的警告部分
So I'm going to put those up here in my alert section here.
这里我#define ALERT_CANT_ADD_PHOTO
So I'm just going to pound sign define can't add photo
为NSLocalizedStringFromTable
to be NS localized string from table.
我需要给它一个字符串
So I have to give it the string.
这里你可以放英语版的文字
And here, one thing you could say here is you could put the English version here.
放英语版的好处在于
And a nice thing about putting the English version here is
在不本地化时 你至少会得到英语
that if you don't localize it, you'll get English at least.
但我不喜欢这个策略
But I actually don't believe in that strategy
因为如果我是法国人 我得到英语 那就会很糟
because if I'm French and I get English, it looks bad.
这让我的app看起来很糟
It makes my app look bad.
更好的做法是使用某种内部定义
It's almost better to get some kind of internal thing
例如说 这个app坏掉了 它会立刻在测试中被找到
that's like, "Oh, this app is broken." It will be found in testing right away.
如果你在app中丢一些英语出来
There's many places that you would ship your app
很多时候 用户都会感到被冒犯
to get offended if you throw English in there.
他们会说 呃 英语 好吧
They're kind of like, "Oh yeah, English. Great."
懂我说的吗
You know what I mean?
因此 最好别这样做
So it's almost better not to do it.
这里还有一个问题 也就是
Also, there's another problem here, which is that what
如果这里只是简单的单词例如alert或yes会怎样
if this word is a simple word like "alert" or "yes"?
这个键只能到表格中去一次
Well, there can only be this key into this table once.
如果yes可能在别的语言中对应两个不同的词
And so if that yes might want to be two different words in a different language,
那就没办法区分它们了
there's no way to distinguish them.
yes是键
You would just yes would be the key,
你只能将yes转为oui或别的什么
and you can only convert yes to "oui" or whatever,
但你做不了别的
but you can't do anything else.
因此这里 我打算将这个内部定义放到这里
So what I do is I actually put this -- this internal define -- into here.
这是键
So that's the key.
这意味着 我必须提供英语.strings文件
What that means is I have to provide an English dot strings
否则这就会出现在UI 因为这是默认值
because otherwise this is going to appear in the UI because that's the default.
我必须这样做
So I'm going to have to do that.
我还要为本地化者提供注释
I also am going to give the comment for the localizer here,
我这里说 这是
I'm just going to say, "This is
用户想添加照片 但存在不可恢复问题时
message given to user if the user tries to add a photo
给用户的警告消息
but there is an unrecoverable problem."
这就是它的作用
Okay. Because that's when this is shown.
当canAddPhoto返回NO时 就会无法添加照片
This can't add photo happens right here with when can add photo returns no.
例如 无法获得地理位置信息
So this is something like, "I can't get where your location is
但这是因为受限
on Earth, but it's because you're restricted.
这时你什么都做不了
So there's nothing you can do about it"
或是 设备上没有摄像头 这时你什么都做不了
or "There's no camera on this device, so there's nothing you can do about it."
哦 按钮错了
Oops, wrong button there.
这是不可恢复的错误
So it's an unrecoverable error.
我这里想解释给本地化者
So I'm trying to explain to the localizer here
这段消息是关于什么的
what this message is about.
我还要把它放到一张表中
And I'm also going to put it in a table.
我使用LocalizedStringFromTable
I'm using localized string from table, and I'm going
表格我将称之为AddPhotoViewController表格
to call the table the "add photo view controller table."
这意味着当我运行genstrings时
So that means that when I run that genstrings thing,
它会生成一个.strings文件称作
it's going to generate a strings file called
AddPhotoViewController.strings
add photo view controller dot strings.
这就是放这个的地方
And that's where it's going to put this.
我将这个视图控制器中的所有这些字符串收集到
So I'm kind of collecting all the strings for this particular view controller
一个.strings文件中
into one strings file.
我可以更细致地分一下
I could separate it even more fine grained,
我也可以将app中的所有字符串放到一个大的里面
or I could put all the strings in my whole app into one big one. That's possible too.
请讲
Yeah?
问题是
Yeah. So the question is:
让本地化者看到英语字符串是否会有好处
Would it be beneficial to let the localizer see the English string?
当然有
Absolutely.
当你把法语.strings文件
And when you send this French dot string --
发送给法语本地化者时
French version of the strings -- off to the French localizer,
英语那个你也要发送 这样他们就可以知道
you'll want to send the English one, too, so they can see, "Oh,
这在英语中是什么
I see what this is in English."
实际上 在我们进行本地化时
And in fact, when we do our localization we're going
我们会从英语开始 然后再到法语
to start with the English one and we'll go to French.
这是这个
So there's that one.
我本地化了这一个字符串
Now, so I've localized that one string right there.
但这里还有很多字符串
But I got a lot of other strings in here.
为了让这个更快一些 我准备了一些代码
So to make this go a little faster I have a snippet here
作用是完成剩余的#号定义 我称其为strings… 对
that does the rest of the pound sign defines, which I've called strings yes.
就是这些了
So here it is.
这些就是其它那些的#号定义
So these are all just pound sign defines for all the other things --
这个已经有了 删掉
actually, I guess I already did that one so we'll do that.
可以看到 这些都有相同的格式
So you can see that they all are the same format, right?
我用了相同的东西 使用AddPhotoViewController
I'm using the same thing there, using add photo view controller.
实际上我的参数顺序有些不同 那是错的
Actually, I had the arguments in a different order there so that was wrong.
首先是表格 最后是注释
So table comes first; comment is last.
把所有这些放到这里
So I put all these in here.
然后我需要在代码中 使用这些东西
And then I just need to go through with my code and use these things everywhere.
例如这个 Add Photo是
So like this one, add photo, is
ALERT_TITLE_ADD_PHOTO
alert; title; title; add photo.
而下面这个是ALERT_DISMISS_BUTTON
And this one down here is alert; dismiss button;
这里也一样
same thing here,
这里 这里 还有这里
and here, and here, and here.
我只需要对所有字符串都这样做
So I just need to do that for all my strings.
出于时间考虑 这个方法我就一次性拼出来
Again, for speed here I'm just going to do it for this method all in one spell.
所有字符串都弄好了
So you can see all the strings in there.
这些都变了 像这样
Now they're all changed, okay, to be like this.
下面滤镜也是一样
Same thing down here with filtering.
滤镜中有很多
So we've got a lot of things here in filter --
动作表单的标题 取消按钮 所有这些滤镜
title of action sheet, cancel button -- all these filters.
把这些也替换掉
So I'm going to replace that as well.
filter…localized
Filter localized.
好了
There we go.
这里也一样
So same thing there.
我做了一样的事
I'm doing the same strategy.
大家都理解我用NSLocalizedString做了什么吗
So everyone understand what we're doing with this NS localized string?
这方面有问题吗
Any questions about that?
现在 我们本地化了我们的app
So now we've localized our app here, but now we need
我们还需要创建.strings文件 然后本地化它
to create this strings file and then localize it.
如何创建.strings文件呢
So how do we create the string file?
当然是使用genstrings
That we do with this genstrings thing.
到Terminal
So let's go get terminal.
这里运行Terminal
So I'm going to run terminal here.
我想这门课上就这一次我会让你们这样做
This is one of the only time I think in this class that I've asked you to do that.
这里我处在主目录中
But here I am in my home directory here.
键入ls
I can do LS.
我在这里
Here I am.
cd到Developer目录
So I'm going to CD to developer.
这是Developer
Okay, here's my developer.
再cd到Photomania
I'm going to CD to PhotoMania.
这样我就到了Photomania的顶层
Now I'm in the top level of PhotoMania.
cd到这个里面去
I'm going to CD inside that.
这是我的所有代码
Here's all my code.
看到了我的.m文件吗
See all my dot M files?
这里还可以看到故事板的lproj文件
And here you can even see my lprojs for my storyboard there.
要生成.strings文件
So the way I'm going to generate the strings file here is I'm
我只需要说genstrings *.m
going to say genstrings star dot M.
这会遍历我的所有.m文件
And that's going to look at all my dot M files, look
看所有NSLocalizedString的宏
at all those NS localizer string macros,
并为所有这些生成.strings文件
and it's going to generate strings files for all of them.
我们这样做了 来看看
So we did it. Let's take a look.
找.strings文件
Start out strings,
果然有了AddPhotoViewController
and sure enough there's add photo view controller
这就是所有表格所用的
because we used that for all the tables here.
如果我们使用别的名称 或是不用FromTable
If we didn't -- say, if we used a different name here or we didn't do from table,
那它就会生成别的.strings文件
then it would have generated other strings files.
但这里我们就生成了这个
But this is the only one we did.
好 让我们拖动那个
All right. So now let's just drag that thing.
先找到它
Let's go find it.
在这里
Here it is.
这是.strings文件
This is the strings file.
AddPhotoViewController.strings
Add photo view controller strings.
我要把它拖到项目中 这里
I'm just going to drag this into my project here.
放到这里
Put it right here.
.strings文件一般都放在view下
Usually we put our strings file all under view.
我们会像这样安放故事板
If we kind of arrange our storyboards into a place,
.strings文件也放到这里
we'll put the strings file there as well because it is part
因为这是关于视图的本地化
of our view, really, the localization of our view.
现在我们有了AddPhotoViewController.strings
And so now we have this add photo view controller strings.
显然 它有所有这些这个等于那个
And sure enough, see, it's got all these things -- this equals that.
好理解吧
Make sense?
下面我们需要让这个.strings文件可本地化
Now we need to make this strings file localizable.
我们到文件检查器这里
We go over here to the file inspector.
这个是文件检查器
This one right here is file inspector.
我选了.strings文件
And I got the strings file selected.
我要点本地化
I'm going to hit localize.
它问 这是什么语言
It's going to say "What language is this?"
这是我们的base
And that's going to be our base,
然后再根据这个来创建英语和法语文件
and then we're going to have English and French created off of that.
这里就选base
So I'm going to leave that be base.
点本地化
So I'll hit localize.
这时我选.strings文件
Now when I select the strings file,
它显示的不是本地化按钮
instead of having a localize button, it shows me a list
而是我在项目设置中设置的各种本地化
of all the localizations that I had set up in my project settings.
我要添加一个英语本地化和一个法语本地化
So I'm going to add an English localization and a French localization.
这样做时 这里我会得到一个小三角
And when I do that, I get a little triangle over here.
可以看到 这是我的base
And you can see here's my base.
然后我有了英语和法语 最开始这只是base的拷贝
And now I have English and French, which it has copied the base to start.
下面我将把这本地化为英语 让我们来这样做
Now I would localize this to English. So let's localize this to English.
我有一段代码 大概在这里
I have a little snippet for that, too, somewhere here.
Photomania 国际化
PhotoMania, internationalization.
这个是英语
This one's English. Here it is.
全选 复制 粘贴
Select all, copy, paste.
这就得到了所有这些东西的英语版
So I've just made English -- the English versions of all of these things.
大家都理解我刚做了什么吗
Everyone understand what I did there?
法语也是一样的
And then French, same thing.
我可以将点插入到所有这些中间
I could take all these and put dots in here,
不过这些我都离线完成了 以便节省时间
but I did that offline to save us some time.
这是这个
That's this.
复制 粘贴
Copy, paste.
我把这个本地化为了法语 用点表示的
So I've localized this to French dot French.
现在我们有了这个的本地化 下面来运行
So now we have localization for that. And so now when we run --
好
okay.
运行时我们发现 还是有些东西需要本地化
So when we run, now we still have some stuff left to localize here.
这些东西还是英语
Right? You can see that these things are still in English.
但到这里 看看这个
But if we go over to here, look at this.
这个上次我们已经看过了
[Inaudible] we already saw that from last time.
我可能忘记提了 地图部分也都本地化了
I forgot to mention that maybe. But the maps part of it is all localized.
到这里 所有这些也有加了点
And when we go over here, we have all these dots.
这些字符串也都本地化了
And now we have these strings also localized.
这里的Add Photo
The add photo here.
我们可以都检查一下
And if we went through and checked them all,
其它那些也都有点
all the other ones would all have the dots, too.
我们在本地化方面取得了不错的进展
So we're making good progress here in terms of our localization.
不过还有一些东西没有本地化
Couple of things, though, not localized here.
一是My Photos
One, my photos, right?
法语中是什么 mes photos还是什么
In French that would be I don't know, mes photos or something.
我不清楚
I don't know.
这里应该是M.y P.h.…
Actually, it would be M dot Y, P dot H dot -- okay.
这个也需要本地化
So we would need to localize that.
这在哪里呢
Where is that?
这在Photographers的这里…
That is here in photographers.
不对 应该是在Core Data中
Actually, no, that's in -- sorry -- that's in core data.
Photographer+Create
Photographer create.
这只是一个字符串字面量
Right? So that's just a literal string.
我们可以将这个用NSLocalizedString本地化
So we would probably localize this with NS localized string.
我不打算做 因为你们已经知道怎么做了
Not going to do it because I've already showed you how to do that.
还有什么没本地化
What else do we have that's not localized?
这一行也没有
This little line right here, zero photos.
或许在法语中这碰巧是正确的
That's actually probably correct in real French.
法语中这个应该也是photos
I think photo is French; in French it's photo as well.
但我们要确保这个可本地化
But we want to make sure that was localizable.
这就是我们要用点的另外一个理由
That's another reason we should do the dot thing
很显然 这里没有点
because it would be obvious that there's no dot here;
如果你只是检查法语翻译 你可能会说
whereas if you're just checking it with French, you'd be like,
哦 对 这个本地化了 其实则没有
"Oh yeah, that's localized," but in fact, it's not.
这在哪呢
So where is that?
在下面这里 这个应该在Photographers里
That's down here in -- that's the one that's in photographers.
它是一个用于表格视图的stringWithFormat
You can see it's just a string with format thing here for table view.
我们希望在这里使用另一个NSLocalizedString
So we would want to do another NS localized string here, right?
然后还有一个是用英语写的
And then there's one other thing that's in English:
这个词Photographer
This word "photographer" right here.
你可能会惊讶 这是哪来的
Now, you might be surprised; where does this come from?
这其实是Core Data表格视图控制器提供的
This is actually being provided by core data table view controller.
几周前我给你们的那个类
That class that we gave you many weeks ago.
在这里 Core Data表格视图控制器
And what happens here is core data table view controller,
在你设置了取回结果控制器后会检查
when you set a fetch results controller, it checks to see
表格视图有没标题
if your table view has a title.
如果没有标题 它就会将标题
And if it doesn't have a title, then it sets the title
设为实体名 Photographer或Photo
to be the entity name -- photographer or photo.
这个的本地化很有趣
Now, this is an interesting one to localize
因为这里我不能使用NSLocalizedString
because I can't use NS localized string here.
都理解为什么吗
Everyone understand why?
因为NSLocalizedString的所有参数
Because NS localized string, all the arguments have
都需要是字面量 @号引号某某
to be literals -- at sign, quote, something.
那这个如何本地化呢
So how am I going to localize this?
我们可以沿NSLocalizedString往下一层
Well, we can go one level below the NS localized string to
到NSBundle
the bundle thing.
我会将这个字符串从这里拿出
So let's take this string. I'm going to take it out of there.
我这里说 NSBundle mainBundle
I'm going to go NS bundle, main bundle,
localizeStringForKey
localize string for key.
这个可以是变量
This can be a variable.
这里设为实体名
So I'm going to make it be that entity name.
value 这是找不到字符串时的默认值
The value, this is the default value if it can't find that string.
这个我设为实体名
So I'll make that be the entity name.
然后table 这是查找的字符串表格
And then table, this is the strings table to look in.
这里我称其为Entities
I'm going to call it entities.
这是我要创建的一个新strings表格
So this is a new strings table that I'm going to have to invent.
如何创建这个strings表格呢
So how do I invent this strings table?
我不能使用genstrings 因为genstrings只能
I can't use that genstrings thing because all genstrings does is look
针对NSLocalizedString 那些宏
at NS localized string, those macros.
如何为这个生成.strings文件
How am I going to make a strings file for this?
我要使用新文件
Well, I'm going to use new file.
新文件 然后到下面这里的资源
So when you do new file, if you go down here to resource --
看到资源了吗 这里有strings文件
you see resource right here -- you'll see that there is strings file.
我要创建一个新strings文件
So I'm going to create a new file, call it strings file.
名为我刚才说的Entities
I'm going to call it entities; that's what I said I called it.
把它和视图那些放一起
I'm going to put it where I keep my view stuff.
点创建
And I hit create.
创建在了这里 Entities.strings
It makes it, it right here. Entities dot string.
我要让它可本地化
I'm going to make it localizable,
同其它.strings文件一样
the same way as I did the other strings file.
这是我们的base 什么都没有
That will be our base, which is nothing.
然后我可以说
And then I can say,
我不需要英语本地化
"Well, I don't need an English localization because
因为数据库中实体的名称都是英语的
the names of the entities in the database are in English."
所以不需要
So I don't need one.
但法语需要
But French I do.
这里我要进行法语本地化
So I'm going to make a French one.
到这里看法语 就是这个
Now if you go over here and look at French, here it is.
然后我可以说Photographer等于Photographer
And now I can just say photographer equals photographer.
这里加上点
And we'll put our dots in here.
点点点点
Dot, dot, dot, dot.
错了
Whoops.
点
Dot.
好 这就翻译成了法语
Okay. So we've translated that to French.
然后我们可以运行看看
And now when we run,
上面的Photographer也本地化了
we'll see that we get photographer along the top here.
这就是需要通过调用Bundle那些来本地化的例子
So that's an example of where you need to localize by actually calling the bundle thing,
这里不能使用NSLocalizedString
as opposed to NS localized string.
有问题
Question?
问得很好
Yeah. Great question.
问题是 使用这些NSLocalizedString时
So the question is: When I did these NS localized strings here
它们都被放在PhotoViewController.m中
I put them in my dot M -- photo view controller dot M --
看到了吗 都在这里面
see how I put them all right in here?
我能否把这些放到.h文件中
Could I put these in a dot H somewhere
然后导入它们 在两者之间共享
and then import them and share them between two?
答案是完全可以
The answer is absolutely you can do that.
genstrings中使用.h文件是完全合法的
When you do genstrings, it's legal to put a dot H file there.
实际上genstrings可以用于任何文件
In fact, genstrings will look in any file you want, right?
没错 你可以那样做
So yes, you can do that.
好
All right.
以上就是本地化了
So that's it for localization.
我只是粗浅地讲了下本地化
I'm just kind of skimming the surface as far as of localization,
不过我认为它很重要
but I think this is a really important one
对于在App商店出售的商品 这是必要的
to know if you're going to ship a product on the app store
本地化能够让你的产品打开市场
because you can really open up your market by having it localized.
本地化这些strings文件的代价并不大
It's not that expensive to have these strings files localized.
更大的代价其实是在质量保证上
Really, more of your cost is sometimes just QA-ing it.
你需要为法国用户提供法语
You got to put something that's in French in front
确保使用了正确的惯用语 确保法国人能够理解
of French users and make sure that it uses the right idioms and that it's understandable.
如果你找到了一家好的本地化公司
And, you know, if you get a good localization company doing the
他们还会为你进行质量保证
localization for you, they'll do the QA as well and make sure that, you know,
确保经受过用户测试
it's actually user-tested as well.
好
All right.
回到幻灯片
Back to the slides.
好 我们要讲的最后一点是设置
Okay. The last thing we're going to talk about here is settings.
设置让你能够添加你的应用程序的
So settings allows you to add user interface
用户界面到通用设置app中
for your application into the general settings app.
看到下方的屏幕截图了吗 这是通用设置app
So you can see the screen capture at the bottom there, that's the general settings app.
在第一页滚动到最底部
And if you scroll down towards the bottom of very first page
你可以看到其它这些app 例如地图
of settings, you can see all these other apps, like Maps
Safari 甚至第三方app
and Safari and even third-party apps --
Twitter Facebook Flickr等等
Twitter, Facebook, Flickr, whatever.
我不确定这些是不是第三方app
Actually, I'm not sure those are third-party apps; they're
或许是iOS7本身集成的
probably iOS 7's integration to those things.
总之 你的app也能出现在列表底部
But your apps could appear at the bottom of this list.
点其中一个app 它就会转到下一个视图
And when you click on one of those apps, it goes to the next view here.
这里我展示了两个 一个是地图的 一个是Safari的
And I've shown two different ones, one for Maps and one for Safari.
可以看到这里有一些UI
And you can see that there are some UI in there.
这里有一些开关
We got some switches,
我们可以从一些预定义的列表中进行选择
we can choose from a predefined list of things
例如这里说搜索引擎谷歌
like where it says search engine Google.
你可以点它 得到一个列表
You can click on that and have a list of things.
这里还可以有滑动条
You can also have sliders in here.
你还可以进行分组等等
You can group things, etc.
你可以对你的app创建这个UI
So this UI you can build for your app
并让设置app做到这个
and have the settings app do this.
这个UI实际是建立在NSUserDefaults上的一层UI
This UI is basically a UI on top of NS user defaults.
UI中的所有这些 都是在设置NSUserDefaults
So these things -- all these things in the UI -- are setting NS user defaults.
这就是它们的作用
That's all they're doing.
这也是同你的app进行通信的方式
And that's how it's communicating with your app.
就这么简单
So it's as simple as that.
这里能放入的UI并不多
There's really not a lot of UI you can put in here.
我不打算一一讲解
I'm not going to talk about all the things you can do.
你们可以自己去看说明文档
You can look in the documentation for that.
不过我说了 滑动条 开关 文本框
But like I said, sliders, switches, text fields,
可键入文本框 还有选择列表 主要是这些
typeable text fields, and also selecting from lists are the main things.
要加入这些东西 做法是在你的app中
The way you add this to your app is in your app, okay,
你到Xcode中添加新文件
you go into Xcode and you say new file.
然后在资源下 选择Settings Bundle
And then under resources you pick settings bundle.
这和刚才我们添加strings文件是相同的位置
This is the same place we went to add a strings file a moment ago.
现在我们选Settings Bundle
Now we're going to do settings bundle.
选Settings Bundle后
And when you do settings bundle
你会得到这个Settings Bundle
you'll get this little settings bundle.
添加到文件浏览器
Add it to your file navigation there.
你可以看到它
You can see it.
它会给你一个默认的样例Bundle
And it's going to give you a default kind of an example bundle,
这很棒
which is really nice
能够帮你开个好头 了解能用这个做什么
because it's a good starting point to get started, and what can I do with this thing?
所有这些UI 不是在故事板中创建
All that UI that you're going to build, you don't build it in a storyboard, you don't
也不是用图形界面来创建
build it, you know, with graphical interface;
而是用属性列表来创建
you build it using a property list.
这个属性列表有定义良好的键和值
And this property list has well-defined keys and values.
这些键和值决定了
And these keys and values determine whether you're doing a
你用的是文本框 还是滑动条 还是分组这些
text field, or a slider, or grouping things, or whatever.
这里你可以看到
So you can kind of see up here some
用于创建这个UI的属性列表
of the property list things you can set to build this UI.
例如 屏幕上
For example, what you see on screen,
我会跟你们展示 它在设置app中是怎样的
I'm going to show you what that looks like in the settings app.
这里有Group 这是项目0
So you see you got a group is item zero.
这个会分组
So this thing is going to be grouped.
组名是Group 它在顶部会说Group
The name of the group is "group," so it's going to say group at the top.
然后我们有一个文本框 一个拨动开关和一个滑动条
And then we got a text field, a toggle switch, and a slider.
看到项目1 2 3了吗
You see items one, two, and three?
文本框在这里 使用字母键盘
The text field there, you know, using the alphabetic keyboard,
不进行自动更正
it doesn't do auto correction,
等等 拨动开关 其标题是Enabled
etc. The toggle switch, its title is enabled.
它会说Enabled 然后这里有个拨动开关
So it's going to say enabled, and then there's going to be a toggle switch there.
滑动条从0到1
The slider looks like it goes from a zero to one.
所有这三个
And for all three of them,
注意到都有name_preference
do you see how it says name underbar preference,
enabled_preference和slider_preference
enabled underbar preference, slider underbar preference in each of those 3 things?
这就是它所设置的NS用户默认
That's the NS user default that it's setting.
我不是很喜欢这些名称 不过这就是它所设置的
I don't really like those names very much, but that's what it's setting.
这个会是怎样的呢
So what is this going to look like? What would this particular thing look like?
它会是这样的
Well, it would look like this.
Group Name Enabled带有一个开关 然后滑动条
Group, name, enabled with a switch, and then the slider.
本地化 我们再来谈谈本地化设置
So localization. Let's talk about localization settings.
设置需要本地化
You've got to have localization for setting,
否则法国人就不知道如何进行设置
otherwise when a person's French they're not going to understand how to do your settings.
做法是使用strings文件
And it's done using strings files.
在Settings Bundle中
And if you look inside the settings bundle,
你可以看到其中有en.lproj
you'll see it comes with an EN dot lproj;
我想这里有点偏向于英文
little bit of English bias there, I think.
在en.lproj中…
And in that EN dot lproj --
实际上可能没有英文偏向性
actually, might not even be English bias.
有可能如果你是法国人 在你开发这个时
It's possible that if you're developing this and you're French,
它会创建fr.lproj
it might create an FR dot lproj for you.
我不知道 我没试过
I'm not sure, I've never tried that.
然后 在这个strings文件中的
And then inside this strings file
是你所创建的UI中会显示出的所有字符串
is every string that would appear in this UI that you're building
等于 它应该等于的东西
with equals whatever it's supposed to be.
无论两张幻灯片前的base plist中是什么
So whatever's in that base P list we saw two slides ago,
UI中出现的一切 你都可以说 它等于别的什么
anything that would appear in the UI you can just say it equals something else.
然后这里可以有任意多个.lproj文件
And then you can have as many dot lprojs as you want here --
法语.lproj等等
French dot lproj, whatever.
糟糕的是 没有办法到文件检查器然后点本地化
The bad thing is there's no way to go to the file inspector and hit localize.
Xcode中不能
For some reason they have not gotten
让Settings Bundle可本地化
around to having the settings bundle be localizable in Xcode.
机制是有 但没有检查器UI来这样做
It's got the mechanism there, but there's no inspector UI to do it.
那如何本地化这个呢
So how do you localize this thing?
如何创建fr.lproj
How do I create an FR dot lproj?
答案是 你要到finder中找到这个Settings Bundle
And the answer is you're going to go to finder and find this settings bundle.
这可以从Xcode中做到
You can actually do that from Xcode.
demo中我会演示
I'll show you how to do that in the demo.
然后右键点击Settings Bundle
Then you're going to right-click on the settings bundle
选显示包内容
and say show package contents.
这会为你显示Settings Bundle中的内容
And that's going to show you what's inside that settings bundle,
它会是这样的
which is going to look like this.
你会看到其中的en.lproj
And you're going to see the EN dot lproj there.
然后你需要手动创建fr.lproj
And now you're going to manually create an FR dot lproj.
这里的支持很好
Really nice support for it here.
通常我会直接复制粘贴en.lproj
And usually I do this by taking the EN dot lproj and just copying and pasting it
然后重命名
and then renaming it
从en.lproj到fr.lproj
from EN dot lproj copy to FR dot lproj.
然后其中的Root.strings
And then the root dot strings that's inside there,
是我要发送给本地化者的
that's what I would send off to my localizer.
它会对法语做等于那些
And that would do the equals thing for French.
我们来看看Bouncer中的这个是怎样的
So let's see what this looks like in Bouncer.
因为Bouncer有些很好的设置我们可以设
Because Bouncer has some nice settings that we could set.
我要让弹球的弹性在设置中可设
And what I'm going to do is make it so the elasticity --
you know, the bounciness of the bouncing ball -- is settable in settings.
当前 弹性是1
So right now we have the elasticity set at one,
这是弹球能够持续往下落的最大弹性
which is kind of the maximum elasticity that it can have and still settle down.
如果大于1 它就会越来越快
If we had more than one, it would start getting faster
在壁间越来越快地弹动
and faster as it bounced off the walls.
这就不会有平等的弹性回弹了
It would be more than an equally elastic rebound.
我们这里让弹性值在0到1之间可设置
So we're going to make it so we can set that elasticity anywhere from zero to one.
0表示撞击后就不再弹起
Zero would mean just kind of hits and dampens immediately.
好
All right.
我们来到Bouncer
So let's go get Bouncer.
Bouncer 这里是Bouncer
Bouncer. Here's Bouncer.
好 Bouncer在上次发布后就没再更改过了
Okay. Bouncer has not changed since last it was posted.
弹性在这里 这个弹性动态的行为
The elasticity is here, this elastic, dynamic behavior.
可以看到 它被设为1 这是当前默认值
And you can see that we set it to one, okay, by default right now.
我们希望能够从设置app中设置这个弹性值
So we want to be able to set this elasticity from the settings app.
首先创建它的UI
So let's build the UI for it first, and then we'll have
然后变更代码 来使用UI将会设定的NS用户默认
to change our code to use the NS user default that our UI's going to set.
创建UI我们只需要点新文件
So to do the UI we just do new file,
来到iOS的资源部分 选Settings Bundle
go to the resource section of iOS, settings bundle.
strings文件相同的地方 Settings Bundle
Same place we did strings file right here, settings bundle.
创建Settings Bundle
Create the settings bundle.
Bundle名叫什么都行
You can call the bundle whatever you want. Doesn't really matter.
我就叫它Settings
I'm going to call it settings.
这里
Here it is.
这是Settings Bundle
Here's the settings bundle.
这个Root.plist就是Bundle的内容了
And this root dot P list is what the bundle is,
其中有四个项目
and you can see it has four items here.
还是分组 文本框 拨动开关 滑动条
Again, group, text field, toggle switch, slider.
每次创建Settings Bundle都会得到这些
So you get this -- every time you create a settings bundle you get this one.
我来看看这是怎样的
Let's go ahead and see what this looks like.
在这里来做
Let's do this over here.
这是我们的Bouncer 它具有完全弹性
So here's our Bouncer, and you can see it's got full elasticity
弹得很好
-- bounces pretty good, right?
我们来到设置app
And if we go over to the settings app right here,
滚动到底部 你会看到其它app之外
if we scroll down to the bottom, you'll see that in addition
这里还有Bouncer
to these other apps, there's Bouncer.
如果Bouncer的图标好点就更好了
If Bouncer had a nice icon, the icon would look better.
点Bouncer 这就是UI
But if we click on Bouncer, here's the UI.
这里有个可以滑动的滑动条
So we got this slider right here that we can move around
还有开关可以关掉
and we've got the switch to turn off.
但这些都没同Bouncer关联起来
But none of this is connected to Bouncer in any way;
这只是创建到设置app的默认东西
this is just the default stuff we got from creating the settings app.
我这里要留下滑动条
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to keep the slider,
并让它从0到1 弹性从0到1
and I'm going to have the slider go from zero to one -- elasticity zero to one.
Enabled开关我打算删掉
I'm going to get rid of this enabled switch right here.
Name文本框我也打算删掉
I'm going to get rid of this name text field right here.
Group我打算保留 但是不再称其为Group
And I'm going to keep the group, but instead of calling it
而是称其为弹性
"group," I'm going to call it "elasticity."
这个UI非常简单
So I'm going to have this really simple UI here
只是设置弹性的滑动条
that says elasticity and then has a slider.
让我们到这里
So let's go here.
删掉文本框
Let's get rid of this text field.
删掉拨动开关
Let's get rid of this toggle switch.
保留Group和滑动条
And so I'm keeping the group and the slider.
将Group改为Elasticity
I'm going to rename the group from group to be "elasticity."
然后在滚动条中 我们看看这些
And then in my slider let's look at some of these things here.
最大值是1
Okay, the maximum value is one.
这很好
That's good.
我希望最大弹性为1
That's maximum elasticity I want.
最小值0
Minimum zero.
这很好 不需要改
So that's good. I don't need to change that,
不过这些显然是可更改的
but you can obviously change these things.
默认值是0.5 不 我希望默认值是1
The default value of .5 -- no, I really want my default value to be one
1才是我希望的默认值 我希望它从这里开始
because that's what my default value was before, and I want it to start there.
然后这个slider_preference很重要
And then this is very important, slider preference.
这是将这个通信回来的NS用户默认
This is going to be the NS user default that communicates this back.
我打算把这称作Settings_Elasticity
And I'm going to call this settings underbar elasticity.
我在为NS用户默认取名时
When I do the names of NS user defaults,
喜欢使用大范畴的名称 例如类名
I like to name scope them, like, with the name of the class
然后下划线 然后项目名
and then an underbar and then all the items in there.
这样就能避免重名的问题
So you kind of give it a little bit of protection against the same name thing.
这里是设置
Here, since this is set in settings,
大范畴于是就是Settings
I'm going to scope it to be settings.
怎么做最好 你们可以有自己的见解
We could argue there are better ways to do that.
不过这种方式很简单
But it's a simple way to do it.
这是代码中我们要用的NS用户默认的名称
So this is going to be the name of the NS user default we want in our code.
下面回到我们的代码
So now let's go back to our code and use
使用这个NS用户默认 而不是1.0
that NS user default instead of 1.0 here.
这里我将删掉这个1.0
So I'm going to get rid of this 1.0.
实际上 我要添加一个方法来做这个
And in fact, I'm going to add a method to do this
叫resetElasticity
called reset elasticity.
让我们写出这个方法
And let's write that method.
void
Void.
resetElasticity
Reset elasticity.
这里我将立刻获取用户默认
And here I'm going to get the user default right off the bat
NSUserDefaults
-- NS user defaults.
你们知道怎么做这个
You know how to do this.
standardUserDefaults
Defaults. Standard user defaults,
valueForKey
value for key.
键是Settings_Elasticity
And the key is settings, elasticity.
或许我们需要进行#define
Again, probably want to pound sign define there, whatever, yes.
不过对于demo 我们直接到这里
But for demo we'll go here.
我要说 如果它已设置
I'm going to say if it's set --
因为它有可能没被设置
because it might be that that's never been set;
有可能用户没有去设置app进行设置
no one's ever gone to the settings app and set this so it might just not even be set.
如果它已设置 那我就会做一件事 如果没设
So if it's set, then I'll do one thing; if it's not set,
如果没人到设置里面去过 那么
if no one's ever gone into settings, then I'm going
我就会将弹性设为1.0 和原来一样
to set my elasticity to be 1.0, which is what it was before.
但如果有人设置过 那么
But if someone has gone to the settings app, then I'm going
我就会将弹性设为这个elasticity的floatValue
to set my elasticity to be this elasticity's float value.
就这么简单
Simple as that.
这对于运行程序之前设置弹性没有问题
Now, this works great the first time we ask for the elasticity.
但如果有人在程序运行时进入设置
But what if someone goes over to settings while my app is running
更改弹性该怎么办呢
and changes the elasticity?
我们需要知道这个 做法是通过一个广播站
We need to find out about that, and we do that with a radio station.
我们会监听又一个广播站
So we're going to listen to another radio station.
这个app中已经监听了两个广播站
We're already listening to two radio stations in this app --
Resign和BecomeActive
the resign and become active.
这里我又要添加一个广播站监听器
So I'm just going to add another radio station listener here.
NotificationCenter defaultCenter
Notification center, default center.
然后… 星球大战跑出来了
And then a little Star Wars there.
然后我们将addObserverForName
And then we're going to add observer for name.
这个我们要观测的广播站
And this thing we're going to -- radio station we're going to observe --
叫作NSUserDefaultsDidChangeNotification
is called NS user defaults did change notification,
顾名思义 用户默认确实更改通知
exactly what you would think it would be called.
我们不关心谁告诉我们它变更了
And we don't care who is going to tell us that it changed.
我们可以在这个队列上来做 这没问题
And we can do it on this queue. It's fine.
当它变化时 我们要做什么
And what are we going to do when it changes?
当然 我们只需要重置弹性
Well, of course, we are just going to reset the elasticity.
这就是单独放到一个方法中的原因
And that's why I put that in a separate method.
它会调用这个 它会读取那个用户默认
So it's going to call this, it's going to read that user default,
更新弹性
update the elasticity.
根据动态动画器我们知道
As we know with the dynamic animator,
弹性值变化后 弹性马上就会受到影响
as soon as you change that elasticity, it's going
to immediately start affecting the elasticity.
我们试试这个
So let's go ahead and try this.
看看能否正常工作
See if this works.
问题是 滑动条的粒度是多大
Yeah. So the question is: What's the granularity of the slider as we move along?
这要看情况
And it depends.
如果是浮点数 你就可以进行任意细的划分
If it's a float, then however wide the slider is, you know,
however many points that can be divided into,
这就是浮点数的粒度
that's how much granularity you're going to get on the float.
如果这里是整数
If it's an integer -- you know, if you're making integer --
那你就会被四舍五入到最近的整数
then you're going to be rounding off to the nearest integer,
这就是从NSUserDefaults得到的情况
right, as you get it from NS user defaults.
粒度一般会取决于可用的宽度
But basically granularity depends on the width available.
这对于不同设备是不同的
So it's actually going to vary per device.
在宽设备上 你能得到更高的粒度
Right? On a wide device you can get a higher granularity.
好 这里弹性是默认值
All right. So here we are; elasticity is default.
这个好难控制
This guy's hard to control.
这里是正常弹性
Okay. So we had normal elasticity going on here.
下面我要到设置app中
So now I'm going to go out to the settings app.
找到Bouncer
I'm going to go down to Bouncer.
这是Bouncer的弹性
Here's Bouncer's elasticity.
它位于1
It's at one.
我要把它调到最小的0
I'm going to crank it all the way down to zero.
这很低 不过没关系
Which is really low, it doesn't matter.
再回到Bouncer
And let's go back to Bouncer.
然后方块落下时 它就不弹了
And now when this thing bounces, doesn't bounce.
低弹性
Low elasticity.
理解了吗
Make sense?
然后我们可以回来
And then we can go back again.
将弹性重新调高
Change the elasticity back to being high.
回到这里 到Bouncer
Back here to Bouncer.
这样就又能弹起了
And now back to bouncing.
理解这里我们做的了吧
Make sense what we did there?
关于这个我还要讲最后一点 也就是本地化
Now, one last thing I want to show you about this is localization.
这里在设置里面显示的是elasticity
So here we have settings elasticity.
这没错 因为现在是英语
Well, that's correct because we're in English.
如果在这里更改语言呢
But what happens if we go and change the language here?
让我们换成法语
So let's go change to French --
国际 语言 法语
international, language, French.
好
All right.
回到设置 到下面找到Bouncer
So now when we go back to settings and we go down to look at Bouncer.
虽然现在是法语 但这里它说的还是elasticity
So we go back here and it still says elasticity even though I'm in French right now.
其它这些都是法语 这很棒
So this is all in French. So we got this all in French -- nice, excellent,
只有Bouncer是英语
all in French, except for Bouncer is English.
这个人会立刻删掉Bouncer
So this person is immediately deleting Bouncer,
这个法国人因为看到英语不爽会立刻删掉Bouncer
this French person deleting Bouncer because of the English bias.
如何修正这个呢
So how do we fix that?
到下面这里
Well, we go down here.
我们要修改这个Root.strings
We want to change this root dot strings right here
写上Elasticity等于Elasticity
to say elasticity equals elasticity.
这是英语中的单词
So this is what we would want in English.
在法语中 我们希望这个是法语单词 或是加点的单词
And in French we'd want this to be the French word, or the dots, or whatever.
如何做到呢
So how are we going to do this?
这里我们需要到文件系统中手动操作
And this is where we have to go out to the file system and do this manually.
做法是选择Settings Bundle
So the way you can go out to the file system is you select the settings bundle,
右键点它
right-click on it,
可以看到第一行就是在finder中显示
and you can see the very first thing here is show in finder.
点选它
So I'll show in finder.
就在这里 但它没有小三角
Here it is, but it doesn't have a little triangle.
因为它是一个包
That's because it's a package.
不过我可以右键点击 选显示包内容
But I can right-click and say show package contents.
这时就会显示出其中的内容
Now it will show me what's inside of it.
这是en.lproj
Here's my EN dot lproj.
我只需要复制粘贴
I'm just going to copy it and paste it.
这就有了en.lproj 2
So now I have EN dot lproj two.
将它重命名为fr.lproj
So I'm going to rename this to be FR dot lproj.
finder处理app的方式中有一点很有趣
What's really kind of interesting about the way the finder works with apps
也就是 这些都会在你输入时同时出现在Xcode中
is this will all be appearing in Xcode at the same time that you're typing it.
这里你不需要做任何特别的事情
So you don't have to do anything special there.
创建目录 重命名
As you create these directories and rename them,
Xcode都能很好地跟踪
Xcode keeps track of it.
这是法语的Root.strings 这个则是英语的
So here's the root dot strings for French and here's the one for English.
在法语的那个中 我们把这个转为加点的
So in the French one let's change this to our dot.
我把这里都加上了点
So we change this to the dots. And now let's -- yeah.
下面让我们来运行这个
So now let's run this.
重新安装Bouncer 包括它的Settings Bundle
Reinstall this Bouncer, including its settings bundle.
好 这里我们有了Bouncer
All right. So here we have Bouncer.
到设置中 看Bouncer设置
Let's go over to settings, look at Bouncer settings,
现在我们有了带有点的elasticity
and now we have elasticity with the dots.
好 这方面有任何疑问吗
All right. Questions about any of that?
请讲
Yeah?
问得棒极了
What a great question.
问题是 我的app里有一些设置选项
Okay. So the question is: If I have settings in my app
用户经常需要进行改变
and the user frequently wants to change them,
例如弹性这些
like let's say elasticity is something that,
用户可能每次游戏都希望有不同的弹性
you know, every game you want to play with a different elasticity
用户希望非常频繁地去设置它
or something like that because, you know, it's not something
而不是设置了就不动了
that you just kind of set to taste and then you just leave it,
这时你就不应该使用设置app
then you would not want to use the settings app.
用户经常要设的东西
Settings that the user wants to set on a regular basis,
应该属于app的一部分
that are a normal part the operation, those want to be in your app.
我们希望有一种方式能在Bouncer中设置弹性
So we would want to have some way here in Bouncer to be able to set the elasticity
可能是某个手势 我们没有使用捏手势
maybe a gesture, maybe, you know, we're not using pinching.
或许捏手势不错
Maybe pinching could do it or something.
我是说 频繁改变的东西 你可以放到这里
I mean, if it's something you want to change a lot, you want it here.
你也可以在顶部放个标题栏
Or you have a title bar across the top
用一个栏按钮来处理这个
and have a bar button for it or something.
设置app里面应该是些设置了以后就不用再管的东西
Really, the settings app is set it and forget it kind of settings.
这些设置用户一旦设定为自己喜欢的样子
Right? Settings that are just maybe something a user tunes
就不会再变了
that they like and then it's set.
这里不应该是需要不断变更的东西
It's not going to be things that you're going to set constantly.
有问题
Question?
问题是 如果我有办法在app中设置弹性
Yeah, so the question is: If I did have a way to set elasticity in my app,
我是否就肯定不应该再在设置app中设置了
should I definitely not set them in my settings?
并不一定
I would say not necessarily.
例如 想想如下情形
Like, for example, you might want to --
假设弹性你每次游戏都想变更
let's say elasticity is something you change with every game.
你点新游戏 然后它就会问你 你想要多大的弹性
Like, you say new game and it says, "What elasticity do you want?"
这时你仍然
It's possible you might want
可以在设置app中去设置默认弹性
to have setting apps set the default elasticity, right,
这时程序问多大弹性时 会从这个默认值开始
so that when it asks you about the elasticity, it starts with that default.
你可能会需要这样做
So it's possible you might want to have that.
不过一般而言 不要把用户搞糊涂了
But generally you don't want the user confused about,
让他们不知道是在这里设置 还是在那里设置
"Where am I setting this? Am I setting it in settings, or am I setting it here?"
这时 在设置app中 你可能需要写默认弹性
So even in that case in settings you'd probably want to call it default elasticity,
而这里 你需要写成弹性
and then here you would call it elasticity or something like that.
问题都很不错
So good questions.
关于设置还有问题吗
Any other questions about settings?
好 本地化和设置
Okay. So both localization and settings, you know,
这些方面你们显然都能做很多事情
there's obviously a lot you can do here.
我这里只是粗浅地讲了一下
And so I'm just kind of trying to skim the surface enough
让你们知道怎么开始
so that you understand where to get started, okay,
涉及到 如何在设置中创建不同的UI
in terms of "How do I make different UI in settings,
以及如何让app可国际化
and what do I do to make my app international-izable?"
好 差不多就这些了
Okay. So that's pretty much it.
这是后面内容的提醒
Here is just a reminder of what's coming up.
我们一开始就讲过
We talked about this at the beginning.
关于期末项目或任何内容有问题的人
If you have any questions about your final projects or about anything else,
都可以来提 我们周三再见
I will be here. And I will see you on Wednesday.
更多内容 请访问我校官网stanford.edu
> For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.